<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<document>
    <properties>
    	<author email="smith@puzzle.ch">Anthony Smith</author>
        <title>About</title>
    </properties>
    <body>
        <section name="About">
        	<p>
				opendbcopy is an open-source project by Anthony Smith, published under the terms of the GNU General Public License. 
				<br/><br/>
				opendbcopy core component can be seen as an application framework providing 
				everything required to run a plugin. Configure a database migration project
				using the opendbcopy graphical user interface.
				<br/><br/>

				<subsection name="Special Thanks to">
					<p>
						I would like to specially thank Mr Blatter (Swiss Department for Defence, Civil Protection, Sports) for
						allowing me to publish opendbcopy as open-source software @sourceforge.
					</p>
				</subsection>
				
				<subsection name="Why did I develop another database migration utility?">
					<p>
						If there is not a need, you normally do not find any software for it. 
						<br/><br/>
						In summer 2003 I was 
						asked to plan and migrate the database of the Swiss Sports Management System (National
						Database for Youth and Sports). The source database was IBM's DB2, running on a host, OS390.
						The destination platform was AIX5.2, Oracle 9i.
						<br/><br/>
						A database migration is normally required when systems are going to be changed. The former
						system was running completely on the host, using DB2 and Websphere 3. The new system is
						built up using Webserver and Application Server Clusters, all running on Linux. The database
						itself on AIX5.2.
						<br/><br/>
						I hope you see what I want to show you. A database migration is normally not just copying tables.
						This includes changes of the application ... and therewith changes of the database schemas.
						<br/><br/>
						So I was looking for a database migration utility which was able to fulfill my special requirements.
						It became obvious that I either have to develop a lot of PL/SQL transformation scripts or develop
						a new utility - opendbcopy.
						<br/><br/>
						I first tried to use Oracle's Migration Workbench, which, on the first glance, looks brilliant. But, but, but ...
						soon I got an answer from their staff that this migration workbench does not support DB2 on OS390. I tried
						out several other ways ... such as migrating into MS SQL first and then into Oracle ... and a lot of other nightmare
						scenarios. However, none of these ways solved my migration requirements elegant enough.
						<br/><br/>
						Even if you have a migration tool that can copy data from DB2 to Oracle, you still need to modify your data 
						according to the new requirements.
						<br/><br/>
						So the idea of opendbcopy began on a Saturday afternoon, when I was waiting for a tram... and 17 
						hours later I had my first implementation of opendbcopy. No GUI, just running from a shell.
						<br/><br/>
						Two weeks later a front end and further features were implemented, so that I was a able to make a 
						first successful database migration.
						<br/><br/>
						At the end of 2003 we made the final migration. I was quite happy that I have developed opendbcopy
						to avoid too much repeated work. Think about how much manpower you need if you choose the 
						conventional way ... extracting data into files, convert the files, write loading and transformation scripts.
						<br/><br/>
						Since then I have used opendbcopy on several other projects. Some of them were again DB2 to Oracle.
						Others were MySQL to PostgreSQL, MySQL to MySQL, MS Access to MS Access (using jdbc:odbc bridge).
						<br/><br/>
						opendbcopy comes with a handful of plugins which can be configured using the plugins.xml. See the 
						plugins section for more details.
						<br/><br/>
						Special requirements can easily be developed. See the developers section for more details.
						<br/><br/>
					</p>
				</subsection>

				<subsection name="Conventional Way versus Online Migration using Java">
					<p>
						By conventional way I understand dumping data from the old database, transfer, convert and prepare
						the data for the new database and last but not least, load the new data into the new database. 
						Taking our projects as a reference this would have involved three people to do that job.
						<ul>
							<li>Dumping data from DB2 requires several utilities and programs ... and a DB2 DBA</li>
							<li>A PL/SQL Programmer to provide data loader scripts, converters and verification scripts</li>
							<li>An Oracle DBA to load the data into the new database</li>
							<li>Repeat above steps whenever you need a further test migration ...</li>
						</ul>
						<br/><br/>
						So far I did not tell anything about generating the new database DDL. In my eyes this is something
						which requires interaction. It would be very simple using opendbcopy or other migration utilities
						to create the CREATE TABLE scripts plain ... but ... have you ever seen a utility, commercial or not, which
						was able to do this for any database system without errors and optimal settings? Next to the CREATE TABLE
						you need PRIMARY KEYS, FOREIGN KEYS, INDEXES, ... 
						<br/><br/>
						I hope to be able to provide soon a plugin which
						is able to do part of this list. If you have any ideas please tell me. An idea I have is creating XDOCLET classes
						with hibernate tags ... and then generate Hibernate mapping files automatically as well as the required DDL.
					</p>
				</subsection>

				<subsection name="Other Database Migration Utilities">
					<p>
						<ul>
							<li><a href="http://dbcopy.sourceforge.net/">dbcopy (Open Source, Eclipse Plugin)</a></li>
							<li><a href="http://octopus.enhydra.org/index.html">Octopus (Open Source)</a></li>
							<li><a href="http://otn.oracle.com/tech/migration/workbench/index.html">Oracle Migration Workbench</a></li>
						</ul>
					</p>
				</subsection>
			</p>
		</section>
    </body>
</document>