<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<document>
    <properties>
    	<author email="smith[at]puzzle.ch">Anthony Smith</author>
        <title>Features</title>
    </properties>
    <body>
        <section name="Features List">
        	<p>

Implemented features can be split into two categories : 
<ul>
<li>openDBcopy Core Features</li>
<li>openDBcopy Plugins</li>
</ul>
</p>
<subsection name="openDBcopy Core Features">
<p>
	openDBcopy's core can be seen as an application framework providing 
	everything required to run a plugin or a series of plugins, a plugin chain. Configure a database migration job
	using the openDBcopy graphical user interface. This includes: 
<ul>
<li>Database Connection Details</li>
<li>Database catalog/schema, options selection and capturing</li>
<li>Tables to process, Table Mapping</li>
<li>Columns to process, Column Mapping, Table specific SQL filters</li>
<li>Global String filters (such as trim, removal of intermediate whitespaces, ...)</li>
<li>Saving a job (plugin chain) or single plugin as XML</li>
</ul>
<p>openDBcopy tries to map tables and columns automatically given its names. 
	To take care of referential integrity constraints let openDBcopy read this extra information.</p>
</p>
</subsection>

<subsection name="openDBcopy Plugins">
<p>
	openDBcopy provides a set of standard plugins. 
	New plugins can easily be developed (see <a href="developer-manual.pdf">developer manual</a>). This includes: 
<ul>
<li>Online Migration of database schemas using Hibernate (including tables, referential integrity, indexes, compound keys, ...)</li>
<li>Online Migration of database data (only logging records which cannot be processed)</li>
<li>Write dump files such as comma separated files (csv), tab delimited text files (txt), ...</li>
<li>Write SQL data scripts (sql)</li>
<li>Comparing number of records for each database and write a nice report</li>
<li>Delete seletected tables</li>
<li>Create ZIP archives</li>
<li>Secure Copy (SSH2) of files, directories to remote hosts</li>
</ul>
</p>
</subsection>	
<p>
	<i>For more information, please see the <a href="user-manual.pdf">user manual</a></i>
</p>
</section>

</body>

</document>