<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<document>
    <properties>
    	<author email="smith@puzzle.ch">Anthony Smith</author>
        <title>About</title>
    </properties>
    <body>
        <section name="Quick Start">
        	<p>
				<i>For more information please see the <a href="user-manual.html">User Manual</a></i>
			</p>
			<br/><br/>
			<subsection name="Download">
				<p>
					Download the latest binary distribution <a href="download.html">here</a>.
					<br/><br/>
					If you have not yet downloaded the required JDBC database drivers for your migration, please do so now.
					Try using the vendor's JDBC driver instead of jdbc:odbc driver. Ensure that your JDBC drivers
					are set in the CLASSPATH or within the /lib directory of opendbcopy.
				</p>
			</subsection>
			<subsection name="Install">
				<p>
					Install the binary distribution using the following command:
					<br/><br/>
					<b>java -jar opendbcopy-xx-install.jar</b> (substitute xx with version number you have downloaded)
					<br/><br/>
					A setup wizard will guide you through the installation.
				</p>
			</subsection>
			<subsection name="Run">
				<p>
					Linux / Mac OS10 / Unix users please use the provided start.sh script to launch opendbcopy.
					<br/><br/>
					Windows users may launch opendbcopy via Icon, Start Menu or start.bat.
				</p>
			</subsection>
			<subsection name="Configure Database Migration Project">
				<p>
					<ul>
						<li>Choose single or dual database mode (in most cases you may want to use dual mode)</li>
						<li>Provide database URL, user name and password if required</li>
						<li>Once tested you can choose catalog/schema to capture</li>
						<li>Once captured you can define which tables shall be processed. 
							If the Destination Table Column is empty click on it and choose from available destination tables.</li>
						<li>On the Column Mapping tab you can specify column mappings for each table marked to process.
							If a destination column is empty, click on it and choose from available unmapped destination columns.
							For each table to process a SQL filter can additionaly be specified and tested.</li>
						<li>Select String filters to apply</li>
						<li>Select the plugin to execute and go for a coffee ...</li>
						<li>Execution log is saved in /logs directory, same for application log. By default all plugins save output within this directory!</li>
					</ul>
				</p>
			</subsection>
		</section>
    </body>
</document>